A Finding Aid to the Jerry Hudson de Leon Papers, circa 1920s-1980, in the Archives of American Art AAA.hudsjerr
Archives of American Art
Jerry Hudson de Leon papers
circa 1920s-1980
AAA.hudsjerr
Archives of American Art
0.9 Linear feet
The papers of illustrator, painter and teacher Jerry Hudson de Leon measure 0.9 linear feet and date from circa 1920s-1980. The papers primarily feature her sketches done in pencil, pen, watercolor and pastel. Also included in this collection are personal letters, various printed materials as well as examples of her illustration work.
Hudson de Leon, Jerry, circa 1905-1980
Biographical/Historical note
Jerry Hudson de Leon (circa 1905-1980) was an illustrator, painter, and teacher from Minnesota. She was a teacher and textbook writer in addition to her freelance illustration work.
Hudson de Leon attended the University of Minnesota and is known for her textbook series for Art Instruction, Inc. where she authored many books such as Commercial Art and Design: The Human Figure Division 8 in the 1950s. Besides writing she also taught art at both the Minneapolis School of Art and the Art Instruction Schools in Minneapolis. She was an accomplished illustrator and painter with one of her paintings, Strike Headquarters, in the collection of the Minnesota Historical Society.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 2012 by Robert Lewis Croft, Jr., a close friend of Jerry Hudson de Leon.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1930-1980 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Notes, circa 1940s (1 folder; Box 1)
Series 3: Photographs, circa 1950-1974 (1 folder; Box 1)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1933-1958 (5 folders; Boxes 1, 3)
Series 5: Artwork, circa 1920s-1950s (0.4 linear feet; Boxes 1-3)
Series 6: Sketchbooks, circa 1940s-1950s (4 folders; Box 2)
Scope and Contents note
The papers of illustrator, painter and teacher Jerry Hudson de Leon measure 0.9 linear feet and date from circa 1920s-1980. The papers primarily feature her sketches done in pencil, pen, watercolor and pastel. Also included in this collection are personal letters, various printed materials as well as examples of her illustration work.
Illustrators--Minnesota; Painters--Minnesota; Sketches; Women artists--Minnesota
- Correspondence, 1930-1980; Series 1; 2 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here are personal letters to and from friends and family, post cards from travels and holiday and greeting cards. Included are letters written to Robin Croft, a friend and fellow artist.
  - Correspondence with Friends and Family, 1930-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Robin Croft, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Notes, circa 1940s; Series 2; 1 Folders Box 1
  Included here are packing lists, lists of sites visited, and notes on the conjunction of Spanish Verbs. These are most likely from her time spent in Mexico.
  - Notes, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Photographs, circa 1950-1974; Series 3; 1 Folders Box 1
  Photographs include various photos of the artist traveling, working, and with friends.
  - Photographs of Jerry Hudson de Leon, circa 1950-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Printed Material, 1933-1958; Series 4; 5 Folders Boxes 1, 3
  Printed material consists of newspaper clippings, ephemera, and other publications in which the artist is featured.
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials, 1937-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minnesota State Fair Ribbons, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Commercial Design Booklet, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Magazine Clippings, circa 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Introducting Your Art School Booklet, 1950-1958 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Artwork, circa 1920s-1950s; Series 5; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Contained within in Artwork are examples of Hudson de Leon's sketches and drawings, painted sketches and illustrations. Included are illustrations as part of a manuscript for the Tanglewood Tales. Found with her chameleon sketches are letters received from the New York Zoological Society, the Smithsonian Institution National Zoological Park and The American Museum of Natural History as well as books and other research materials regarding chameleons. Besides sketches and watercolors of Mexico, there are also sketches of designs, portraits, and city scenes. The board illustrations contain figure studies and portraits. The undated painting of a woman is an oil study on board.
  - Illustrations for La Gringa, circa 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dog and Cat Sketches, circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chameleon Sketches, Letters and Research, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sketches and Watercolor Studies of Mexico, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Various Sketches and Watercolors Studies, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Oversized material housed in Box 3, Folder 2.
  - Sketches for Tanglewood Tales, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Artwork by Others, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Various Sketches and Watercolor Studies, circa 1940-1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 14.
  - Board Illustrations, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Final Illustrations for Tanglewood Tales, circa 1940s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Painting of a Woman, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Sketchbooks, circa 1940s-1950s; Series 6; 4 Folders Box 2
  Found here are four sketchbooks highlighting Hudson de Leon's various travels through the United States and Europe and experiments with new styles of illustration such as Japanese brushwork.
  - Japanese Brush Drawings Sketchbook, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - North Africa and France Sketchbook, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Travel Sketchbook, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Travel Sketchbook, 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)